BETH: Many individuals with autism
are perfectly able and willing to
work, but only 21.7% are in full
or part-time employment, due to the
barriers they face in gaining employment.
JOE: Individuals with autism can offer
a wide range of skills and knowledge,
qualities and attributes to an employer,
however the field of employment is
a challenging and full of barriers
which many struggle to overcome.
These barriers may be different
for each individual depending on
where they are on the spectrum.
BETH: Some employers do not recognise
the difficulties that these barriers
pose and may be unintentionally or
purposely restricting employment
opportunities for individuals with autism.
Most of these barriers can be removed,
or reduced, by making 'reasonable
adjustments' when necessary.
JOE: Barriers may start whilst
trying to find a suitable job.
Search results may be confusing
and the information vague
especially through recruiters.
This can create uncertainty as to
who is the employer, how much does
the job pay, what are the hours?
BETH: Filling in application forms may
cause problems with difficult questions
to answer about gaps in work history
and why they left a previous job, and
psychometric or personality tests.
Questions about health or disability
may mean disclosing their autism
at the application stage which
may put employers off reading
their CV or offering an interview.
Negative assumptions and limited
knowledge can stop an employer
processing the application.
JOE: Some individuals are themselves put
off applying, due to negative experiences
of previous applications or interviews.
Attending an interview can be really
daunting as they may find it hard
to know what to do, what to expect.
They may have problems anticipating
questions and will be worried about the
process if they have not done it before.
There may be other things involved
such group interviews, tests,
activities or presentations,
these can all cause great concern.
BETH: Eye contact and verbal and
non-verbal communication which
is often key in interviews may be
a problem, and how to respond to
‘question and answer’ sessions.
Once the interview is over, they
may be unsure about how they did or
how it went or when they might hear.
JOE: Success at the application and
interview stage may not alleviate
the issues of starting the job
and going through the process
of signing contracts and other
formalities can itself cause issues.
Let alone other elements such as when
they start the job, the daily routine
and deadlines for projects, what do
they wear, how should they behave,
when are their breaks, what are
their hours, holiday allowance, and
adjusting to the workplace environment.